Guide to the Montana Department of Highways, Missoula District Office records 1927-1988
Montana Historical Society Research Center
Montana Department of Highways, Missoula District Office records
1927-1988
Montana Historical Society Archives
RS 421
Montana. Department of Highways.
5.8 linear feet of shelf space
Records of the Montana Department of Highways, Missoula District Office, consisting primarily of correspondence, both internal and inter-departmental, dealing with procedural, personnel, and project-related topics. There are also frequent communiqués from the Federal Highway Administration.
The Montana State Highway Commission was created in 1913 by the state Legislative Assembly. The original Commission was composed of three members. In 1917 new legislation altered the organization of the Commission by authorizing the appointment of twelve members according to geographic highway districts. Membership was changed again in 1921 to three members appointed by the Governor and in 1941 to five members, also appointed by the Governor. In 1971 the Commission was renamed the Montana Department of Highways, created by Chapter 7 of the Executive Reorganization Act of 1971 and implemented by executive order of the Governor on December 16, 1971. The Department of Highways took over all but the advisory functions of the State Highway Commission.
By 1972, the Department consisted of seven divisions: the Legal Division, Personnel Division, Centralized Services Division, Engineering Division, Motor Pool Division, Gross Vehicle Weight Division, and the Maintenance Division. Each division was headed by an administrator. The Centralized Services Division, Engineering Division, Motor Pool Division, Gross Vehicle Weight Division, and the Maintenance Division were furthered sub-divided into bureaus, headed by Chiefs. In 1991, the Department of Highways became the Department of Transportation.
The Highway Department, the Department of Highways, and Department of Transportation maintained regional offices in five districts: Billings, Butte, Glendive, Great Falls, and Missoula. The District Engineer (later called the District Administrator) was the chief administrative officer in each district office. District office files document the activities of the district administrators, engineers, maintenance crew, and other district office employees. The district offices addressed administrative, functional, and project related issues of their particular area, including: highway needs, current construction projects, training for employees, road design, federal and state aid and grants, and reports to the Department of Highways/Department of Transportation in Helena.
This collection consists primarily of correspondence documenting district office activities, including: notifications of, and judgments on, encroachment of highway right of way; training needs and requirements for personnel; departmental policies and procedures; signing on Montana highways; plowing, sanding, speed limits, crossing lights/walks, and other pedestrian and driver safety measures; testing roadway durability; and scheduling roadway projects, such as resurfacing and widening.
It should be noted that the Archives is only in possession of the Department of Highway, Missoula District Office records, and did not receive any accompanying Missoula District Office records from the Department of Transportation.
This collection is arranged by series.
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition information available upon request
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the Montana Historical Society Archives catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search under these terms.
Roads; Transportation--Montana; Highway engineering--Montana; Roads--Design and construction--Montana
Montana
Detailed Description of the Collection
- Correspondence
  - General Correspondence, 1927 >May–1977 August (Box 1)
  - General Correspondence, 1977 September–1982 February (Box 2)
  - General Correspondence, 1982 March–1983 December (Box 3)
  - General Correspondence, 1983–1985 December (Box 4)
  - General Correspondence, 1986 January–1987 December (Box 5)
  - General Correspondence, 1988 January–1988 July (Box 6)
  - General Correspondence, 1988 August–1988 December (Box 7)
- Minutes
  - District Staff Meetings, 1984-1986 (Box 7)